Guide to the James Herbert Morse Poetry Collection 1873-1923 MS 3233
New-York Historical Society
James Herbert Morse poetry collection
1873-1923
New-York Historical Society
Morse, James Herbert, 1841-
MS 3233
.75 Linear feet In two manuscript boxes
The James Herbert Morse poetry collection contains poetry manuscripts and typescripts written between 1873 and 1923 by James Herbert Morse. The collection also includes a published volume of poetry written by Morse.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged by material type. The first box of bound materials (notebooks and printed material) is arranged chronologically. The typescripts in the second box, while bound, have a considerable amount of loose pages within them.
Biographical / Historical
Born on October 8, 1841 in Hubbardston, Massachusetts, James Herbert Morse was an author, educator, classical scholar, and literary figure in New York City. After attending Harvard and graduating with a B.A. in 1863, Morse then went on to get a M.A. in 1866. Two years later, he founded the Morse and Rogers Classical School in New York City, where he taught students Greek and Roman literature and history. Once in New York, Morse became a prominent and active member of various literary and social organizations such as the Century Club, the Greek Club, and the Author's Club. In addition to his work as an educator and social figure, he wrote and published various articles, poems, and essays in publications such as Century Magazine, Harper's Monthly, The Atlantic, and the Anti-Slavery Standard. In 1886, G.P. Putnam's Sons published one volume of his verses, Summer Haven Songs.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open to all qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Amelia Bacon, great-great-granddaughter of James Herbert Morse, September 14, 2022.
Related Materials
In addition to the James Herbert Morse poetry collection, the New-York Historical Society also houses Diaries, 1866-1911 (Mss Collection BV - Morse, James) as well as the Personal Recollections of the Draft Riot of 1863, circa 1927 (Mss Collection AHMC - Morse, Lucy Gibbons) written by Morse's wife, Lucy Gibbons Morse.
Scope and Contents
The James Herbert Morse poetry collection includes notebooks, manuscripts, typescripts, and a published volume of poetry. Dating from 1873 to the early 1900s, the collection reflects Morse's passions for literature and creative writing. It includes a volume of his verses, Summer Haven Songs, published by G.P. Putnam's Sons in 1886.
American poetry -- 19th century.; Poets, American -- New York (State) -- New York.; Poetry, Modern -- 19th century.; Manuscripts (documents); Typescripts.
- Poetry notebooks and published work, 1873-1901 (Offsite-box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Box 1 includes the bound portions of the collection, including 4 notebooks of manuscript poems, a printed copy of Summer Haven Songs (New York and London: G.P. Putnam's Sons, 1886), and a printed pamphlet, Harvard College -- Class of 1863. Verses by James Herbert Morse. Read June 25, 1901, at the Class Dinner.
  - Poetry notebook "Vol II", 1873 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 1)
    General
    The first notebook of manuscript poems has "Vol II Poems & Index" written on the front pastedown, measures 19 x 12 cm., and includes 195 pages numbered by Morse. The first poem is dated Jan. 1, 1873. Most poems appear to be fair copies, though some show Morse's corrections. Includes a 7-page index at the end of the notebook.
  - Poetry notebook "Vol IV", 1884 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 2)
    The second notebook of manuscript poems has "Vol VI Poems 1884 & Index" written on the front flyleaf and "Vol IV Poems" written on the first page. This is likely Vol IV since another notebook is also labeled Vol VI. The notebook measures 20 x 13 cm. and includes 73 pages numbered by Morse. The index is not included in the page numbers. The front of the notebook is dated: "Cotuit, Mass. July, 1884." Most poems look like fair copies, though there are occasional notes by Morse. Poems printed in Summer Haven Songs have "SHS" written in the margin. Includes a 2-page index at the end of the notebook.
  - Poetry notebook "Vol V", 1879-1883 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 3)
    The third notebook of manuscript poems has "Vol V Poems & Index" written on the front pastedown, measures 21 x 14 cm., and includes 193 pages numbered by Morse. The front flyleaf is signed: "J.H. Morse, 112 West 38th St., New York." The notebook is not dated at the front of the volume, but dates within the text range from 1879 to 1883. This notebook feels more like a working notebook, with copius edits by Morse and quotations from John Milton, George Herbert, Edmund Spenser, William Wordsword, and other English poets tipped in on pieces of paper. Includes a 2-page index at the end of the notebook.
  - Poetry notebook "Vol VI", 1884 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 4)
    The fourth notebook of manuscript poems has "VI" pasted to the cover, "Vol VI Poems" written on the front pastedown, and "43 W. 39." written on the front flyleaf. There is also a pasted bookseller's ticket: "A. Turnbull, Books & Stationery, 663 6th Ave., N.Y." The notebook measures 22 x 14 cm. and includes 155 pages numbered by Morse. The notebook is not dated at the front of the volume, but some of the poems are dated 1884. Many of the poems are fair copies, but some include Morse's edits. He has marked poems published in Summer Haven Songs with "SHS." This notebook does not include an index.
  - Summer Haven Songs, 1886 (Offsite-box 1, Volume 5)
    A green cloth-bound copy of Morse's Summer Haven Songs, published in New York and London by G.P. Putnam's Sons in 1886.
  - Harvard College--Class of 1863. Verses by James Herbert Morse. Read June 25, 1901, at the class dinner. (Offsite-box 1, Volume 6)
    A printed pamphlet (8 pages) of Morse's poems read at a Harvard class dinner for the Class of 1863. The upper left corner is inscribed by Morse: "Compliments of the author."
- Manuscripts and typescripts (Offsite-box 2)
  This box includes one folder of manuscript poems and four folders of typescript poems.
  - Manuscripts (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    Fair copy of Morse's poetry collections Winter Sonnets, Fireside Musings, and Sonnets of Spring (titles taken from Morse's table of contents.)
  - Titled typescripts (folder 1) (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes typescripts of "Home Pictures" and Other Poems and "A Backward Glance."
  - Titled typescripts (folder 2) (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
    Includes typescripts of "In Softer Tones" and Other Poems and In Nature Poems Miscellaneous.
  - Sonnet typescripts (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
    Various sonnet typescripts, including named collections Under the Stars, Sonnets of Travel, In My Parlor, Sonnets of Song, Religious, Meditative, and Miscellaneous.
  - Miscellaneous typescripts (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
    This folder includes typescripts without specific title pages and loose typescripts.